Shark cartilage supplements
are promoted
by some alternative
medicine practitioners
due to their supposed
anti-cancer properties.
Is there any truth to that?
Let’s find out.
"The Truth About
Shark Cartilage Pills"
An assessment of websites on
complementary and alternative medicine
for cancer found that many
endorse unproven therapies
and some that are outright dangerous,
potentially exploiting highly
vulnerable patients
and enriching irresponsible
snake oil peddlers,
or for that matter, shark
cartilage peddlers,
accounting for millions of
dollars of sales every year.
Why shark cartilage of all things?
Interest in shark cartilage
as an anticancer agent arose
because many people believe
that sharks did not get cancer.
Why would they think such a thing?
Because some shark cartilage supplement
hawker wrote a book called,
"Sharks Don't Get Cancer."
But that's simply not true.
Sharks do get cancer.
Both benign and cancerous lesions have
been reported in 21 species of sharks
more than 9 families.
For example, this oral tumor spilling
out of the mouth of a great white.
Now some shark cartilage distributors insist
instead that sharks just rarely get cancer,
but actual cancer rates in sharks
have never been determined.
There's simply been no
systematic tumor surveys of sharks
for them to make such a claim.
But look, even if sharks were
less susceptible to cancer,
how can one logically jump from that
to cancer patients benefiting
from eating powdered
cartilage from a shark?
We know, for example, that there
are certain proteins that allow
some bacteria to survive in
like boiling hot springs.
Uh, does that mean if we eat those bacteria
we can survive boiling water, too?
It doesn't make any sense.
The illogic behind the pursuit of shark
cartilage therapies has implications
beyond the reduction of shark populations
and the misdirection of patients
to ineffective cancer therapies.
The stuff may be harmful,
and I'm not just talking about
the rare case of shark
cartilage-induced liver inflammation.
Shark products can contain the neurotoxin
BMAA, which I've talked about before.
It's been detected at elevated levels
in the brains of Alzheimer's
disease and ALS patients,
and may play a role in the development
of neurodegenerative disease.
So like the consumption
of shark fin soup or
something may pose a significant health risk,
but what about shark cartilage supplements?
They tested sixteen commercial shark
cartilage supplements, right off the shelves,
and found BMAA in fifteen out of sixteen.
But look, even if shark cartilage supplements
carry pro-inflammatory properties,
which could pose a potential health risk
for consumers, we're talking about cancer.
There are chemotherapy agents that
are life-threateningly dangerous,
but sometimes the benefits can outweigh
the risks when confronted with cancer.
So the question then becomes: are
there any benefits to shark cartilage?
I mean, it's not a completely whacky idea.
Cartilage, in general, is highly resistant
to invasion by tumor cells,
so maybe there's some cartilage-
derived anti-invasion factor?
Less interesting alternative explanations
are that it's just hard for the cancer
to penetrate the cartilage, or perhaps
because of the poor blood supply
in cartilage, cancer doesn't consider
it particularly fertile ground.
But maybe that lack of blood vessels
in cartilage can be exploited.
The reason that no blood vessels
end up in cartilage is because
cartilage cells produce
angiogenesis inhibitors,
blood vessel creation inhibitors.
And so maybe we can starve tumor growth
by infusing these cartilage factors.
What scientists do is implant
tumors into the eyeballs of rabbits,
so they can visualize how many blood
vessels the tumor is able to draw to itself.
And indeed, shark cartilage contains
inhibitors of tumor angiogenesis.
Such findings made the sales
of shark cartilage skyrocket,
driving two shark species
to the brink of extinction.
But cow cartilage does the same thing.
Here, they used bovine cartilage.
And so does human cartilage,
for that matter.
So why sell shark cartilage?
Well, it does sound so much more exotic,
and sharks have like 10 times
more cartilage per animal.
One 20-foot shark could net
like 50 pounds of cartilage.
Just because cartilage has blood vessel
inhibiting chemicals in it, though,
doesn't mean if cancer patients
eat it, it will help them.
It's kind of like magical thinking: shark
cartilage stops blood vessel growth,
thus, by consuming shark cartilage,
humans will somehow be protected.
I mean, the shark cartilage protein
molecules would seem to be
too large to be absorbed by the gut.
It's not like you're injecting shark cartilage
into your bloodstream through an IV.
But there was this rat study
that did find that
just feeding shark cartilage to the animals,
you could cut down on blood vessel
growth within their bodies.
OK, but does that translate out to stopping
the growth and spread of cancer?
Apparently not, as none of the
shark cartilage doses tested
had any retarding effect on cancer
growth or spread in tumor-bearing mice,
but just because it doesn't work in rodents
doesn't mean it doesn't work in humans.
To find that out you need
to put it to the test,
evaluating shark cartilage in human
cancer patients, which we'll cover next.
When it comes to marketing
unproven cancer treatments,
the Internet has become the Wild West.
Fraudsters are able to take advantage
of people like never before.
"Cancer Patients Find Quackery on The Web,"
bemoaned the National Cancer Institute.
Did you know there were more
than 200,000 documents
about cancer on the web?
What? When was this published?
Oh, 1996.
That's just a few years
after the web was born.
Not to worry, though, said the author of
Dr. Linden's Guide to Online Medicine.
It takes a lot of time and money
to maintain a Web page.
So don't worry, the mass of information
on the Internet will dwindle
during the next few years
as the Internet matures.
Right! Yes, dwindling from 200,000
down to a mere quarter of a billion.
And one the most commonly recommended
"alternative cancer cures"
on popular websites is shark cartilage.
Much has been made in recent years of
the mystical aura afforded to the stuff.
Clearly part of it is the visceral fear of
cancer, combined with a healthy respect
for a creature that's survived basically
unchanged since prehistoric times.
It has been reported that
sharks rarely get cancer,
and their skeleton is
made out of cartilage,
and so logic has led some to believe
that this must be the reason
for sharks' relative health.
Not exactly sure that's logical,
but they do have a lot of cartilage.
Cartilage, in general, has few blood vessels,
and blood vessels are
important for cancer growth,
and all this conspired to prime fraught
cancer patients for shameful exploitation
by pseudoscience and
the supplement industry
with the addition of just one myth,
and that's sharks don't get cancer.
But they do get cancer, after all.
Just another layer of fallacious arguments,
successfully convincing desperate cancer
patients to buy ineffective products.
But wait, you don't know if it's
ineffective until you put it to the test.
Sixty patients with a variety of advanced
cancers, given like a dozen scoops a day
of shark cartilage, and not
a single, even partial, response
was noted in any of their tumors.
Ineffective with no salutary
effect on the quality of life.
In fact, suffering significant
gastrointestinal toxicity from the stuff,
all the while the tumors
progressed in all the patients.
But what's missing from this survival graph?
What happened in the control group?
There was no control group.
So while this is what you'd expect
to see in advanced cancer patients,
how do we know the cancers wouldn't
have progressed even faster
without the shark cartilage?
That's why we need
randomized controlled trials,
but there weren't any until
the Mayo clinic stepped up.
A randomized, placebo-controlled,
double-blind, clinical trial
for patients with incurable breast
or colorectal carcinoma.
Data on a total of 83 patients were analyzed,
and there was no difference in survival
between patients getting shark cartilage
versus those getting placebo, nor any
suggestion of improvement in quality of life.
There was evidently
a prostate cancer study, too.
Only 5 patients were even
able to complete the study,
and in all five their cancers
continued to progress unabated.
So unfortunately, the claims for
the benefits of shark cartilage
are completely unsubstantiated
by any objective data
from controlled clinical trials.
Not so fast, said
supplement manufacturers.
Maybe these crude commercial
shark cartilage powders just
don't have high enough levels of whatever
active components there may be,
so cancer patients should instead be
taking shark cartilage extract pills.
So the National Cancer Institute said fine,
we'll test that, too, just
to make absolutely sure.
And so they funded a randomized,
double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial
to put it to the test.
Unlike the other shark cartilage
dietary supplement studies,
they used the purified extract, and
the study outcome was unambiguous.
It failed.
The shark cartilage group lived 14 months,
and the placebo group lived 15 months.
So no significant difference in survival
or to time to progression
or tumor response rate.
So these clinical studies suggest
shark cartilage is not just
an unproven cancer remedy,
but actually a well disproven one.
Yet despite the overwhelming evidence
to the contrary such claims persisted.
For example, the huckster who started it all
wrote a sequel, "Sharks Still Don't Get Cancer."
Perhaps the only cure for this
myth is to spread the rumor
that cartilage from the noses of
such quacks fights cancer, too.
Anyway, if you really wanted
to eat angiogenesis inhibitors,
why sit down to a bowl
of cartilage powder,
when you could just eat an apple, or drink
green tea, or turmeric, or pomegranate,
berries and nuts, soybeans,
flaxseeds, broccoli---
all of which have been shown
to have anti-angiogenic effects.